[SPEAKER_00]: Do you have any direct method to overcome this sense of ownership?
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplate, through your ownership, that which you own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take up that which you regard as yours, and then see how, or rather where, it is rooted at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether in your sense of control, or whether in something else that it isn't yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, the body, take up the body, my body, is that sense of my body, is that the center of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, would this body be depending upon all these individual organs within that sense of ownership of this body, that are required to be operating, that I cannot control?
[SPEAKER_01]: If those organs were to fail, would I be able to entertain the notion of this body as mine, if this body dies right... right in front of me?
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's... You realize that you couldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're perverting the order by regarding... by giving the priority of that sense of self, of my master, of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when you think about the individual organs, you don't think about them within that sense of master.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think about left, right, before or after.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you don't uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the closest to a method would be to contemplate within this ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't leave the ownership out and contemplate things rightly, because the whole point of contemplation is to experience the non-ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you experience the non-ownership when you see that this body, no matter how much it's in your control, its heart is rooted in that which you cannot even conceive controlling, such as heart, breathing lungs, pumping blood, operating organs, functioning brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive how it would be to control those things or have say in their operating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, they are the fundamental basis for the notion of your body as a whole that you do own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mistaken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because we think we come, we, myself, comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I come first, thus this is for me, this is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because I take all this to be mine, I develop a sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that sense of I am can be undone, not by denying it, or by saying, oh, there's no self, there's not really me, look, everything is changing, this is not... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to take up that sense of I am,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, see that it's founded upon things that cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, automatically, your experience is the experience of not-I-am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reversing the mistakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Draining, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Draining them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The kind of the structure stays the same, but what has drained away is that appropriation from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha would say, for an arhant, it's like a palm stump.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cut at its root.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the stump, the branches that grown, they stayed, but now they're then done.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're petrified.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're still there, as the way person's experience might have proliferated throughout the ignorant life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, once you uproot that ignorance, once you remove that appropriation, it stops proliferating and then just stays like a palm stump, until even that breaks apart in parinibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you lose that or get rid of that sense of ownership, your personality doesn't... how does your personality... Well, anything in your personality that was depending upon the ownership, that will disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are other things that were not depending upon ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were depending upon like hollow habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Habits that were not rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, as I said many times, and in the suttas you read often, people cannot tell an arahant externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even another arahant cannot come and see the, I don't know, some special aura around him, oh, he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can tell an arahant when they start
[SPEAKER_01]: Discussing each other's understanding of dhamma, and then you can see, oh yeah, he understood this, probably to the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, then the Buddha, or somebody with very, very developed mind, could see little traits, little things, based on which he could tell the other person's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on an average, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even like Sariputta couldn't tell, in some cases, that the person was an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you go to the Buddha and said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Where was his rebirth?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, what do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Didn't he say he was an arahant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he did, but he was associating with some... not some reputable families and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, that's... that's not why a person is blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: A person is blameworthy because they leave this body, they take another body, as in they keep... remain bound with saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I can tell you he wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wasn't blameworthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was an arahant even before he died.
[SPEAKER_01]: But Saripuri couldn't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the... or the other, that famous one, who was like really harsh in his speech, and the people were often offended.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, oh, it's his old habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not rooted in ill will or greed or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, he would come across as very angry, furious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, that doesn't mean like, oh, okay, so I don't have to... You will know that... You will know which habits can stay once you're an arahant or on the way of becoming one.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't decide that beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, these are my...
[SPEAKER_01]: Neutral habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to take them all with caution.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're in a state of putujana, you can't trust any of your habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep investigating any of it, if it's rooted on greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And truly, truly, when you dismantle everything that shouldn't be there, whatever's left, then you know that can be left.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's very different from saying that the self doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the Buddha never said that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he asked him, does the self exist?
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does the self does not exist?
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's a... it's a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a quick fix, in terms of satisfying explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not a contemplation when you say there's no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, all these rocks, they're constantly changing electrons and atoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just a hollow convention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Conventional speech and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's... that's not what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can say that yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because conventions are real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you might not call it self, but the thing is that phenomena that you refer to yourself, it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it weren't there, you wouldn't be able to refer to it whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, dismissing the reality does not remove your ownership of that reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, ah, so I should be concerned with me appropriating reality, not being concerned about dismantling conventions and proving that nothing exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, instead of treating the illness in regard to the body, you just go and chop up the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And say, see, the body can be chopped up, thus it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a collection of parts that can be chopped up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is that self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, what you should do is remove the ownership of that sense of self, and then it becomes anatta, as in not myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's a practice of denial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, I don't want to say not myself, because then people might assume, ah, someone else's self.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta is self that you don't own, and that cannot be called self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that which was taken as self, still there, but now it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taken as not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people are concerned with denying that which is taken as self, which is an aspect of their experience, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as the Buddha said, the five aggregates are not the assumption, are not the holding the view of the self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no view of the self apart from the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's desire and lust in regard to the five aggregates that the view of self is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: By you coming and saying there is no self, the five aggregates are impermanent, there is no self, you're just dismissing it, the problem, and without actually understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to... if you were to truly understand it, well, the only way to truly understand it is to free yourself from that self, to see it as not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any explanation that you think you understood, unless it's freeing you from that sense of self, don't think you understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people can put a lot of time and effort in denial practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, unfortunately.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many of the meditation methods and techniques are all based on that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just denial and seeing the moment-to-moment movement, they will kind of show you that somehow things are not really real, cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that whole practice goes completely against being
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-transparent, honest, authentic, saying this, I do experience this self, I do experience this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is mother, there is father, there is given, there is offered.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no gender.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, okay, people can deny anything, whatever they please.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the attitude, yeah, it can be aimed literally at anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said the right... the worldly right view is the view that acknowledges the validity of random phenomena, of phenomena in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, there is this, there is that, there is given, there is the... there is mother, there is father, there is the liberation, there is the path, allowing... Like, you don't need to see them, and of course, you don't see them at that level, but you need to know that there is a possibility of them being... being real, as in there is a possibility of being free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you keep denying everything, you will never accept that possibility as a present phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the key.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accepting possibilities as a present negative phenomenon in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know how to what extent, but I could find out if I apply myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to deny anything, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to restrain yourself from what you were told it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed averse delusion that you can see that it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, within that, you don't need to deny further.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be like overshooting the mark.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to understand what's in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole universe is contained within this less than six foot long body and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't say his body is not real, thus none of the universe is real, thus there is no travel, there is no mother, there is no father, there is no life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there were those views at the time that he quite heavily criticized.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, nobody gets killed, there's nothing, it's just elements, just... And actually, modern interpretation of Buddhist anatta, it's actually one of those wrong views back in the day that the Buddha criticized.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they say everything is comprised of constantly changing electrons, so nothing is real or nothing can be mine, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people believe that, whereby they said, oh, nobody gets killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you go and cut everybody on the left side of Ganges with a sharp sword, nobody gets killed.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that happens is the sword runs through the elements, runs through the electrons and atoms.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just call it whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: The view is the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will say it's completely wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're blaming the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, person who is not freed from the sense of self, when the five aggregates disintegrate, as in when they die, they're still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: They get reborn.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reminds me of when someone's got a problem and it's like, you know, complaining about trying to talk it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, I don't know the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But anyway, anyway, everything's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, anyway, it's OK.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I've got this problem, but I'll just deny it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, unfortunately, it's prevalent as a view, but it's just rooted in lazy self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in self-reflection, it doesn't go far enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you just put a cap on it by saying, ah, well, it's all impermanent anyway, so I won't bother with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just, you know, watch my breath and be peaceful and live a simple life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can live life as simply as you want, as a vegetable, and still remain equally ignorant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not how complex your life is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, you want to simplify it, because it can be too much, like, to start with, to practice, but that's secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just creating the suitable condition for you to understand what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But thinking that the goal of your life is to simplify, or to just do this, just do that, without making the effort to understand it, and go through that unpleasantness of unraveling the deep existential feelings of fear and anxiety, yeah, there's no practice without that.
It's not like that.